The דף *daf* is דף פ״ד *daf pei daled*
and we pick up with the very bottom of פ״ג עמוד ב׳
*pei gimel amud bet*. The immediate topic under discussion is that a
boat is not מקבל טומאה tumah *mekabel tumah*. The משנה Mishnah, *mishnah*
learns it from a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* as all משניות mishnayot *mishnayot*
do in this פרק *perek* דרך אניה בלב ים *derech oniyah b'lev
yam* comparing the boat to the ocean.
But חנניה Chananya, *Chananya* learns it out from a more general principle
that if something made out of wood is only טמא tamei. *tamei*
if it is able like a שק *sak*, it is able to
be carried empty and full and a boat cannot. And the obvious
difference as the גמרא Gemara *gemara* pointed out yesterday was that that
is not a categorical exclusion of the boat, that's only things that
satisfy those criteria. So therefore if you have a boat for example
that could be carried, like a canoe, when it's full and that
you carry and portage, which is presumably what the גמרא Gemara *gemara*
means when it says to ספינת הירדן sefinat haYarden. *sfinat hayarden*, then
according to חנניה Chananya *Chananya* it would be טמא tamei. *tamei*. It's
not a categorical exclusion of boat. Another example would be something made
out of non-wood like the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says pottery. For חנניה
Chananya's *Chananya* it is specifically a הלכה halacha, *halacha* relating to things
that are made out of wood, not a categorical exclusion of boat.
So we now continue as the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says like this.
So that's why, that's what חנניה Chananya בן עקביא *Chananya ben Akavya*
says, חנינא בן עקביא *Chanina ben Akavya*, not the same חנניה Chananya,
*Chananya* we started with, that the reason a ספינת הירדן sefinat haYarden.
*sfinat hayarden* is טמא tamei. *tamei* is because you carry it on
the dry land. So now we say אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav
Yehuda, אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, six lines from the
bottom. Says רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* in the name of רב *Rav*,
לעולם אל ימנע אדם את עצמו מבית המדרש *Leolam al yimna adam
et atzmo mibeit hamidrash*. A person should never hold himself back from
being in the study hall. You should always seize every opportunity to
be in the study hall. ואפילו שעה אחת *Veafilu sha'ah achat*, even
for one hour you shouldn't go and be doing something else if
you have the opportunity to be there. שהרי כמה שנים נשתנתה משנה
mishna זו בבית המדרש *Sheharei kamah shanim nishtantah mishnah zu b'beit hamidrash*,
many years this משנה mishna *mishnah* that the ספינת הירדן sfinat hayarden,
*sfinat hayarden* can become טמא tamei *tamei* was taught in the study
hall, ולא נתגלה טעמה *v'lo nitgalah ta'amah*, and we always taught it
but we were never able to understand it, it was never revealed
the reasoning behind it, עד שבא רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina בן עקביא
*ad sheba Rabbi Chanina ben Akavya*, until Rabbi Chanina ben Akavya came
along, ופירשה *ufirshah*, and he explained it because a ספינת הירדן sfinat
hayarden, *sfinat hayarden* is something that is carried on dry land and
therefore it is because it can be carried empty and full it
can become טמא tamei. *tamei*. So things that we might be very,
very familiar with, you never know, one day some brilliant new idea
might come up and explain things even things that are well known
to us. So you should always seize every opportunity to be in
the בית מדרש *beit midrash*.
Why would he choose such an obscure thing?
But it's so self-evident. That's a good question. It's self-evident maybe. It's
self-evident if you explain that the reason is presumably based on this
idea: can it be carried empty or full? If you're following the
משנה mishna *mishnah* and you're basing it on this idea that it's
a categorical exclusion, then you would have no idea why to exclude
the ספינת הירדן sfinat hayarden, *sfinat hayarden*. Or maybe what you would
have done is you would have made a distinction between ים *yam*,
a boat that goes in the ocean, and a ירדן *yarden*, something
that goes in a river. But it is a good point, of
all the things to say, why pick on this? I don't know.
And if you didn't know it, what would change? There are so
many practical...
It's a good point, it's a good point. I don't know why
this was of all things picked as that example. אמר רבי יונתן
*Amar Rabbi Yonatan*, now it's interesting to contrast what רב *Rav* said
to what רבי יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan* said. Said רבי יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan*,
לעולם אל ימנע אדם את עצמו מבית המדרש *Leolam al yimna adam
et atzmo mibeit hamidrash*, a person should never hold themselves back from
being in the study hall, ומדברי תורה Torah, *umidivrei Torah*, and forget
the study hall, just learning תורה Torah *Torah*. ואפילו בשעת מיתה *Veafilu
b'sha'at mitah*, even at the moment of death, שנאמר Shenemar, *shenemar*, זאת
התורה אדם כי ימות באהל Zos HaTorah adam ki yamut b'ohel. *Zot
haTorah adam ki yamut b'ohel*, this is the תורה Torah, *Torah*, a
person who dies in the tent. אפילו בשעת מיתה *Afilu b'sha'at mitah*,
even
at
the moment of death, אדם כי ימות *adam ki yamut*, they עוסק
בתורה *osek baTorah* should be זאת התורה *zot haTorah*. Now the
difference is is that the previous statement is very pragmatic concern. It's
that don't not be away from the בית מדרש *beit midrash* because
there'll be some new idea and you won't have had a chance
to hear it because you weren't there that day. So it's about
the result, it's about attaining the knowledge.
This statement is less about attaining the knowledge and more about the
attitude and the act of always learning תורה Torah. *Torah*. Meaning even
if it's the moment of death, you're never going to use this
תורה Torah. *Torah* again in your life because you're only living for
this last minute
and it's not necessarily about going to the בית המדרש *beit hamidrash*.
Going to the בית המדרש *beit hamidrash* is you hear other people's
ideas. He also mentions you shouldn't stop learning תורה Torah *Torah*. You're
not going to come up with any new ideas, you're not listening
to other people, I mean you yourself could sometimes, but obviously you're
just learning on your own, maybe you're reviewing something you know. You're
not going to use it later because you're about to die, but
it doesn't matter. The idea that every moment of life, just the
value of cleaving to תורה Torah *Torah* every moment for its own
sake, not because of some result that you'll get out of it,
even a תורה Torah *Torah* result, that is in itself the core
value. And now we have the statement of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
*Resh Lakish*, the famous one, אמר ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אין דברי
תורה Torah. מתקיימין אלא במי שממית *Amar Resh Lakish ein divrei Torah
mitkaymin ela bemi shemamit* And this I think is a nice merger
of the two ideas. The תורה Torah only is established on somebody
that will kill himself over it, meaning like this self-sacrifice, you're willing
to like, you know, give up all of your energy and time
and really exert 110% effort, only if like you're willing to kill
yourself over it, self-sacrifice. שנאמר, Shene'emar as the פסוק pasuk says, זאת
התורה אדם כי ימות באהל.
This is the תורה, Torah this is the way תורה Torah is
achieved, if a person dies in the tent, in the tent of
תורה, Torah you know, figuratively dies for the sake of learning תורה.
Torah So what I see ריש לקיש is a nice bringing together
of these two. One said you should always be around because you'll
learn new ideas. The other said, forget about what you're going to
learn, you should always be learning, you know, for the sake of
learning even to the last moment of your life just for the
sake of always being involved in תורה. Torah Where ריש לקיש says
is that if you have that attitude, if you have that approach,
that you're always sacrificing for the sake of תורה Torah because of
your passion of תורה Torah for its own sake, the result will
be is that that will create the best way in which תורה
Torah is established in you. So you know, you'll achieve the end
result, you know, by this sort of by this fundamental
approach of always sacrificing for the sake of learning תורה. So that
was a very nice little digression from the focus about the boat
and ספינת הירדן. sfinat hayarden. And now we get back to the
ספינת הירדן. So now the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
so says רבא Rava back down to the top of פ"ד עמוד
א', peh daled amud aleph, ולחנניה, ul'Chananya, and according to חנניה, Chananya,
טלטולא ידי שוורים שמי טלטולא. taltula yedei shevarim shmai taltula.
So חנניה Chananya was the one that emphasizes that something has to
be able to be carried empty or full, right? And that a
boat is normally not unless it's like a canoe. Okay now actually
תוספות Tosafos points out that the רבנן Rabbanan don't disagree with that
principle. Right? That's a general principle. They just say in addition there's
a special category of boats that are excluded even when boats don't
satisfy that category. But nevertheless, although the rabbis don't really disagree with
חנניה Chananya approach, we are focusing here on חנניה Chananya because he's
the one who said it. So according to חנניה, Chananya, or framed
more generally, according to those that say the idea here is that
if something can be carried,
it can become טמא. tamei, So not only being carried by people,
even טלטולא ידי שוורים שמי טלטולא, taltula yedei shevarim shmai taltula, even
carried by oxen is considered its being able to be carried.
תוספות Tosafos points out obviously carried by the ocean would not count
because then boats would be טמא. tamei. Okay but there clearly it's
the sea is really like sort of moving and the ground is
moving under it. It's different when it is the thing is
stationary and the ground is moving under it. It's very different when
the ground is stable and you're moving it or you're using animals
or oxen to move it. So that is also considered movable and
can become טמא. tamei. דתנן... Detnan...
Right, I know, דתנן Detnan we taught in the משנה, mishna שלוש
עגלות הן. shalosh agalot hein. There are three types of wagons.
עשויה כקתדרא, Asuya k'katedra, if it's made like a cathedra, meaning
like a like a place of sitting, like it's basically a type
of a covered wagon made for people to sit in, then טמאה
מדרס. tmeia midras. Then it is טמא tamei the טומאה tumah, of
מדרס, midras, of the, you know, of seats where a זב, zav,
זבה, zavah, נידה niddah as we've been saying sits or reclines on
something and it's made for sitting and reclining, doesn't just happen to
sit and recline. They lie on a table that's not טומאת מדרס.
tumat midras. But they sit or recline on something that's made for
that purpose, then it becomes an אב הטומאה av hatumah even if
they did not touch it. And that's called טומאת מדרס tumat midras
specifically for a זב, zav, זבה, zavah, and נידה. niddah. So the
point here is that if you've got this covered wagon that is
made for, you know, maybe a stagecoach is a better idea than
thinking about this covered wagon, it's specifically made for people to ride
in, then that if you sit in it, it's, you know,
it is טמא. tamei. Now the point is, טמאה מדרס, tmeia midras,
okay? So one minute, so that's number one, that it can become
טמא מדרס. tamei midras. כמטה, K'mita, if it is like a bed,
which רש"י Rashi basically says means like a, what'd you say, what
like although a long bed, what do they call those things that
have those long narrow, not a long bed, a long something? Something.
No, no, no, but what I'm talking about like you're talking about
like think about a truck, right? Or like a flatbed, that's what
I'm thinking about, a flatbed. Right? So the same use of the
word bed, but the point here is, you basically have a wagon
that is used for transporting goods, not for sitting in. Like a,
so like a long thin truck that is not used for sitting,
it's used for transporting goods. So that type of a case it
cannot be טמא מדרס tamei midras because it's not made for people
to sit in it. But טמאה טומאת מת. tmeia tumat met. It
is טמאה טומאת מת tmeia tumat met because it is, because it
is still used for carrying stuff even though it is not used
for sitting. Okay, so that would be a טומאה, tumah that would
be meaning it could be any other טומאה tumah. except מדרס. midras.
It's still a vessel. It could still become טמא, tamei except that
it cannot be מדרס midras because people don't sit in it, it's
not made for sitting in it. Now, של אבנים, shel avanim, let's
say you have a truck that is used for carrying, for carrying,
no,
for carrying stones, okay, then טהורה מכלום. tehora miklum. Then it's... Then
it is totally טהור. tahor. Why is it totally טהור? tahor? Because
רש״י Rashi says the way they would make this type of thing
that's for carrying stones is you know stones like boulders or whatever
would be large, and if the the floor of it would be
like a crisscross of of wood bars with big holes in them,
right, like not a you know not a straight floor like crisscross
with big holes, so therefore wooden vessels that have holes bigger than
the size of a pomegranate are not טמא. tamei. It needs to
be a wooden vessel that's able to be a receptacle and even
though this functions as a receptacle for the boulders you're using, the
boulders you're using, it doesn't matter. If it's a wooden vessel with
a hole in it bigger than the size of a pomegranate, it
cannot be טמא. tamei. So those are the three categories. If it
has too big of a hole, no; used for carrying people, it
could be מדרס; midras; used for carrying goods, then it could be
all other טומאות. tumos. Now one second. Now, why can it become
טמא tamei. by use for carrying goods? If you use it to
carry goods, right, you've got this big wagon that you load up
with tons of you know whatever, you know beer or you know
corn or whatever goods you load up with, there's no way you
can carry the wagon. What makes it a vessel, right? It's not
able to be carried; it's a wooden vessel that can't be carried.
So, ah, so this is the answer. Because it's pulled by horses
or it's pulled by oxen. So you see that the definition of
being able to be carried does not just mean being able to
be carried by people. Even if it can be carried or moved
by oxen, that also qualifies. Okay, so let's just read this. דאמר
רבי יוחנן ואם יש בה בית קיבול רימונים טמאים טמאי מת. D'amar
Rabbi Yochanan v'im yesh bah beis kibul rimonim t'mei'im t'mei meis. And
if, however, that that thing for stones, it does not, it has
holes, it can't, it doesn't have holes that are what do you
call it, that are the size of, that are the size of
pomegranates, the holes are smaller than that size, it would be טמא.
tame. So the biggest proof is from this last case, because maybe
you'd say the first case is talking that you would load it
up with light stuff, but here we're saying even something that carries
stones, it will become טמא tame if it doesn't have big holes.
How do you carry it? So the point is you don't carry
it, but your oxen drag it and that is considered to be
able to be carried. Okay, yeah, so right, there was a question
here first, yes.
Is the boat and the way it has to be wood, right?
Yeah, we're talking about wood. Wood things have to have this quality
of being able to be carried when they're loaded up.
And what about the person who's actually sitting on this wagon who's
doing the, you know, having to work with it, so where he's
sitting there?
Oh, that might be, but I think we're talking about that like,
you know, you'd maybe be sitting on the on the horses, I
don't know, you're right, I'm not exactly sure, it's a good question,
right, if you were to sit in a part of it, the
front part, maybe that would be able to be מדרס, midras, right.
Yeah, that's an interesting point and how would you subdivide the thing
if it was all one piece. Right, yes, Michael you have a
question? No. Okay, רבקה?
Rivka? ואם יש בה קיבול רימונים טמאים, V'im yesh bah kibul rimonim
t'mei'im, you said that means it doesn't have.
No, meaning it can receive רימונים, rimonim, which means the holes are
not bigger than pomegranates. If it can, if it is a receptacle
for pomegranates, can be used as a receptacle for pomegranates, so what
does it mean can be used for a receptacle for pomegranates?
It means it doesn't have a hole,
if it doesn't have a hole the size larger than a pomegranate,
then it is. Okay, yeah, I know, I sort of I skipped
the step, but that's what it means, if it can receive a
pomegranate, which means the holes are smaller than a pomegranate, then it
can become טמא. tame Yes.
Why did they use a Greek and Latin word קתדרא? catedra?
Because that was part of their vocabulary. I don't know, these are
words that felt, you know, we have that.
Are there not perfectly adequate Hebrew words? I understand. So were they
trying to accomplish something, is there a particular meaning?
Right, right, I understand.
ואם יש בה, V'im yesh bah,
if it has in this thing for carrying stones the receptacle is
it can hold pomegranates, then it is טמא. tame, Meaning the receptacle
is the floor of this wagon and if that floor of the
wagon could hold a pomegranate, meaning even if the whole floor couldn't,
let's say a section of the floor maybe could, you know I
don't know, a subdivided floor and you could put stuff in this
half and it wouldn't have holes, you know, but if there was
a section that could hold pomegranates then it would be a wooden
vessel that had a receptacle.
So would any space that's at all
that's big enough to hold a pomegranate?
Right, but effectively hold it. Meaning if you had like a flat
expanse of wood that was bigger than a pomegranate, but if you
tried to put a pomegranate on it it would roll off and
roll into the hole, that doesn't count. Right, but if you had
a piece of it that would effectively hold a pomegranate, that would
be a בית קיבול beis kibul and then it would be טמא.
tame.
So imagine any surface that doesn't have enough flat.
No, you have a big crisscross with a lot of holes on
the bottom, right, there's not, yeah, it would be that that's not
unusual at all. Okay.
This way the hole has to be smaller than a pomegranate because
if it was larger than a pomegranate
the pomegranate would just fall through. But if one of those gaps,
right, is less than a pomegranate, anyway that's the point. All right,
let's go on, let's go on. I have to say this, it's
not
100% relevant but I once read this article to me it's just
so brilliant about like this trivial little innovation that completely transformed the
whole shipping industry. industry, which is the idea of the containers, which
is, you know, normally what they would do is you'd load up
a boat with barrels or whatever you'd load it up with. Then
you'd have to take off those barrels and you'd put them into
trucks or whatever, and it was just an extremely, you know, labor-intensive
process. What somebody did is they came up with this idea that
you have these huge containers, these rectangular, you know, things that are
all pretty much standard size. You fill them up and what happens
when the boat comes into shore? You use a crane, you pick
it up, and you put it on a flatbed of a truck.
Yep. That one idea,
לא זו היא מידת המדרש, Lo zu hi midat hamidrash, that one
idea, you know, saved billions of hours and, you know, of labor
and of money and so whatever in the shipping industry.
So anyway, mine is the dock workers are about to go on
strike.
Okay.
Anyway, now we go on. תנו רבנן. Tano Rabbanan. Okay, so now
the rest of the Mishna. Now we just quote the end of
the Mishna. We're not really going to make a point about it,
but we're just—since we quoted this Mishna about the wagons, we're going
to quote this end of the Mishna. שלש תיבות הן, Shalosh tevot
hen, there are three boxes,
chests you might say. תיבה שפתחא מצדה, Teva shepitchah mitzidah, if you
have a chest, a box that you can open on the side,
טמאה מדרש, Teme'ah midras,
it's Tamei Midras because, you know, it's very often, you know, what
what do you do? If you have a nice, like, wood, you
know, chest, and you know, you'd sit on it. Very often people
use those chests to sit on. Of course, if you have to
say, get off, I need to get something from it, it doesn't
count as a seat because you—because its primary, you know, you're using
it as a seat interferes with its primary use. But if the
access to the stuff is from the side of it, then you
could equally use it as a seat and therefore if it can
become Tamei Midras if a Zav or Zavah sat on it. Okay,
that's a box with an opening on the side.
טמאה מדרש. Teme'ah midras. מלמעלה, Milamalah, if you, however, access it from
the top, then it cannot become Midras because that interferes with its
main use. But טמאה טמא מת, Teme'ah tumat met, it can become
all other Tumot including the heaviest which is a Tumah of Met.
Now, והבא במדה, Vehaba bemidah, if it comes in size, Rashi says
he doesn't know exactly what that phrase means but it means like
it's a huge sizes. In that case, טהורה מכלום, Tehorah miklum, it
is completely Tahor because again, it would be something that when it
would be filled up would not be able to be carried. So
if it's one of those huge size boxes, then it was a—then
it would not—if it was a—one of those containers we were talking
about. Yeah, so so
the—well, yeah, that's good. Go ahead. Go ahead.
The monstrous containers are in container ships. We can't carry them, an
animal can't carry them, but a flatbed truck or a crane can
carry them.
Right. So that's what, you know, so that—right, so that was Michael's
question about what constitutes שיעורין, shiurin, you know, nowadays. The other question
I think relevant to be asked, because nowadays almost anything could be
carried by a truck except like—not like the Queen Anne, that maybe
not, you know, like a huge ship, that wouldn't.
But—but the other question is, do we just mean not your case—I
mean your case would be it's usually used by these flatbed trucks,
but let's say it's a case of this box. In theory, if
you got it on a wagon the oxen can drag it, but
it's not made to be dragged by oxen as opposed to like
the wagons we were talking about when the Gemara included something that
could be dragged by oxen, presumably it meant something that was made
for that purpose. Okay, but it does raise the question how you
would translate that nowadays.
Which way do we hold by?
Do we hold by that ships are ships or do we hold
by that—Yeah, the Gemara has not clearly concluded. It does seem that
everybody agrees to this principle something has to be able to be
carried. The question is, and if not, it's not Tamei. The question
is, is there an additional category of ships that's just excluded regardless?
Okay, now we continue. I should say one other point that's going
to be relevant as we—in the next point, which is this idea
that there has to be able to be carried, you know, carried
when it's filled to be Tamei. That's only for all other Tumot.
For טומאת מדרש, Tumat midras, for the Tumah of seats, that doesn't
follow those normal rules. Okay, all other types of Tumah which is
it receives Tumah from the outside, if you imagine it like that,
that has a lot of these criteria we've been talking about. Okay,
but טומאת מדרש Tumat midras as we're going to see is different.
Okay, so—so the—if it's something that's used as a seat and a
Zav or Zavah sits on it, then even perhaps if it doesn't
satisfy those criteria that we just mentioned. But just keep that in
mind as we continue now looking at the Gemara. So the Gemara
says like this, תנו רבנן. Tano Rabbanan. מדרש כלי חרס טהור. Midras
klei cheres tahor. If a Zav or Zavah or whatever sits on
a—something made out of pottery, even if it's made for being sat
on. Okay, you've got some I don't know pottery stool or something.
It doesn't matter. That cannot become Tamei, it cannot be in the
category of a Midras.
רבי יוסי אומר—We'll Rabbi Yose omer see, we'll
see. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, אף אספינות. Af asfinot. Even
boats. מאי קאמר? Mai kamar? What do you mean even boats? Who
was talking about boats? And what do you mean
so? So אמר רב זביד הכי קאמר, Amar Rav Zevid hachi kamar,
this is how to read it. מדרש כלי חרס טהור. Midras klei
cheres tahor. Number one, pottery vessels cannot become a Midras. That's a
categorical exclusion. But implicitly or maybe now it's being written to say
explicitly, ומגעו טמא, Umaga'o tamei, of course, if you touch it. If
a זב, zav, if you touch a כלי חרס, kli cheres, or
let's say a זב zav touches the inside of a כלי חרס,
kli cheres, obviously it'll make it טמא. tame. It's just an exclusion
from the category of מדרס. midrash. It's not an exclusion from other
categories of טומאה. tumah, Okay, that's about pottery vessels. Then we say,
וספינה של חרס, Usfina shel cheres, remember yesterday we mentioned the pottery
boat? If you happen to have a boat made out of pottery,
in that case, טמאה כחנניה. tme'a kechananya. That would also be טמא
tame. like חנניה, Chananya that boats are not categorically excluded. Now, it
would also only be טמא tame, by touch, not by מדרס, midrash,
because pottery is categorically excluded from מדרס. midrash. So pottery vessels are
excluded from מדרס, midrash, but now we're reading the תנא קמא tanna
kamma to say pottery vessels cannot be מדרס, midrash, but they can
have other טומאות, tumaos, you know, if you touch them, and that
includes boats. Okay, a pottery boat is like anything else made out
of pottery. And then, רבי יוסי אומר, Rebbi Yossi omer, now we
will understand what רבי יוסי'ס Rebbi Yossi's response is. רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yossi says, no, אף הספינה טהורה, Af hasfina tehora, that's not true.
Boats are also
טהור, tahor, כדתנן דידן, kedatan didan, even if it's made out of
pottery, a boat is categorically excluded. Okay? So we have again this
משנה mishnah. that mentions boat, which is obviously very relevant to our
discussion, but it's not exactly clear what the context is. So we
read it through the lens of our משנה that the תנא, tanna,
that the first opinion is saying pottery vessels are not מדרס midrash
but they are other טומאה, tumah. including boats. And רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yossi says, no, boats are completely excluded, even pottery boats. Okay, so
מתקיף לה רב פפא, Matkif lah Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa
asks on this, מאי אף? Mai af? So then what does רבי
יוסי Rebbi Yossi mean, even boats are טהור? tahor? Who said anything
is טהור? tahor? We're talking about things being טמא, tame. right? The
way it's phrased is pottery vessels are not מדרס, midrash, but they
are other טומאות, tumaos, and boats also are the same, pottery boats
are the same, other טומאה. tuma And רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi says,
no, even boats are טהור. tahor. Even in addition to what? Right?
All we've said is that things are, I mean, we're not talking
about מדרס, midrash, we're talking about other טומאות. tumaos. We're talking about
things being טמא. tame, So what do you mean even boats are
טהור? tahor? So מאי אף? Mai af? אלא אמר רב פפא, Ella
amar Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa says the same thing, except
he switches the order. He reverses it. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, מדרס
כלי חרס טהור. Midras kli cheres tahor. Sitting on a כלי חרס,
kli cheres, a כלי חרס kli cheres does not become a מדרס,
midrash, ומגעו טמא, umaga'o tame, however, obviously if you touch it on
the inside, it's a pottery vessel, it will be טמא. tamei, It's
just excluded from the מדרס midrash category. ושל עץ, Veshel etz, now
if you're talking however, not about pottery, but you're talking about other
materials like wood, בין מדרסו בין מגעו טמא, bein midraso bein maga'o
tame, whether as a seat or whether touching, it's
טמא. tamei, Non-pottery vessels can become all טומאות, tumaos, even including מדרס.
midrash. Okay, that is
non-pottery. וספינת הירדן, Usfinat hayarden, and now we're introducing the ספינת הירדן,
which we also mentioned yesterday. So notice the two לשונות leshonos of
this גמרא Gemara. are touching on like yesterday's
גמרא Gemaras was a setup, was laying the groundwork for this. It
mentioned two excluded categories, pottery and a ספינת הירדן, like a canoe.
So now we have this debate around boats, and it's not exactly
clear what we're talking about. So the first approach said we're talking
about pottery boats, that the תנא קמא tanna kamma says pottery boats
are a problem, and the second one says like חנניה and the
other says not. Now we're going to the other approach, we're talking
about the ספינת הירדן, the rafts, the same issue that's debated between
חנניה and the חכמים. chachamim. Okay? So this says other things like
wood are טמא, tamei, but ספינת הירדן טהורה, sfinat hayarden tehora, that
would be טהורה tehora even though it's made out of wood. Why?
כדתנן דידן, Kedatan didan, like our תנא, tanna, it's a categorical exclusion
of boats. Now so this has the first opinion saying that a
ספינה sfina is טהורה, tehora, not טמאה. tme'a. Okay,
so it is טהורה. tehora. Now רבי יוסי אומר, Rebbi Yossi omer,
no, אף הספינה טמאה כחנניה, Af hasfina tme'a kechananya, a ספינה sfina
is also טמאה. tme'a. Okay? So clearly רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi and
the תנא קמא tanna kamma here are arguing over a certain type
of a boat. So first thing we have to do, we have
to figure out what type of a boat would they be arguing
about. Where yesterday we set up that there are two types of
boats that would be a difference between חנניה and the חכמים, chachamim,
pottery or a canoe. According to the חכמים chachamim that they're categorically
excluded, those also would be טהור. tahor. According to חנניה, it's about
being able to be carried in wood and so on, those would
be טמא. tamei. So those are the two types of things that
can be debated. So here we have a debate of רבי יוסי
Rebbi Yossi and the חכמים chachamim about a boat, it's talking about
one or the other of the boats, either the pottery or the
ספינת הירדן. And according to the second version, the first, we have
that the תנא קמא tanna kamma is saying that it is טהור
tahor and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi is saying אף הספינה טמאה, Af
hasfina tme'a, the even now works. The same way you said other
wood vessels are טמא, tamei, a boat is no different, a boat
is also טמאה. tme'a. And that is like חנניה if we're talking
about a boat that can be carried. Okay, so with that, we
sort of put an end for the time being this discussion about
boats, that it's a debate about whether it's a categorical exclusion or
for these particular reasons. And now we have said the נפקא מינא
nafka mina is pottery or a canoe, and we've read that into
this משנה to being one or the other of those. Now that
we've introduced this idea that a pottery vessel... Okay, so that was,
we sort of put end for the time being this discussion about
boats, that it's a debate about whether it's a categorical exclusion or
for these particular reasons, and now we have said the נפקא מינה
nafka mina is pottery or a canoe, and we've read that into
this משנה to be being one or the other of those. Now
that we've introduced this idea that a pottery vessel cannot become a
מדרס, midras, then we want to understand why. So let's take a
look. ומדרס
כלי חרס מנלן דטהור? U'midras kley cheres minalan d'tahor? How do you
know that if a pottery vessel is used specifically as a seat,
how do you know it's excluded from the category of מדרס? midras?
אמר חזקיה, Amar Chizkiya, דאמר קרא d'amar kra as the פסוק pasuk
says, ואיש אשר יגע במשכבו, v'ish asher yiga b'mishkavo, if a person
touches his seat, the seat of a זב, zav, so he'll become
טמא, tamei because that's the idea that a משכב, mishkav, which is
one of the מדרסות, midrasot, one of the things that a זב
zav sits or rests on, is an אב הטומאה. av hatuma. So
it—but it says his seat. מקיש משכבו לו Makish mishkavo lo is
to connect his seat to himself, it's his seat. מה הוא אית
ליה טהרה במקוה אף משכבו נמי אית ליה טהרה במקוה. Ma hu
it lei tahara b'mikva af mishkavo nami it lei tahara b'mikva. So
the same way he, when he becomes טמא, tamei goes טהור tahor
by going to a מקוה, mikva, so his משכב mishkav can only,
the only thing that will become a משכב mishkav of a זב
zav is something that can be taken to a מקוה mikva to
make טהור. tahor. Something like pottery vessels that cannot be taken to
a מקוה mikva to be made טהור tahor are not. Now you're
shaking your head. Besides for saying it's a גזירת הכתוב gzerat hakatuv
and it's arbitrary, in a way you also do understand the logic
that you don't want his seat to be more strict than the
status that relates to him himself. His own personal status is a
temporary one, right, is going to after he'll go to the מקוה
mikva after seven days it'll go away. So how should it be
that the thing he sits on gets a permanent status? If he
himself, his status is only temporary. So therefore it won't apply to
pottery vessels because the תורה does not allow for the purification process
of pottery vessels. It says when a pottery vessel becomes טמא, tamei,
the תורה always says you have to shatter it and break it.
What?
It's not serious.
The תורה isn't serious?
When they say breaking it.
Are you asking? It is, according to הלכה, halacha. you don't have
to break it if you don't want to use it, then you—I
mean or if you want to keep it טמא.
tamei, But it's טהור tahor but it's useless?
Or well, if you break it, you could break it, and once
you break it and it's let's say it's no longer usable, I
mean there's a question, there are משניות in כלים Keilim that discuss
how much you have to break it, like right,
let's say the simplest example would be it's in three pieces so
no one piece is the majority of the size, then it loses
its טומאה tuma and then you can put it back in a
kiln and then use it again. But you cannot take it to
the מקוה, mikva, you can keep it the way it is if
you want to keep it טמא, tamei. but if you want to
get it טהור tahor you have to break it and then refashion
it.
And then put it back together, the pieces back together.
I don't know, I don't make pottery. No, I mean הלכתית. halachicly.
Oh yes, you could. If you did הלכתית halachicly put it back
together, then it would remain טהור. tahor. That is correct. There is
under some circumstances there's a rabbinic טומאה tuma that is if you
put it back together the old טומאה tumah comes back. But, but
okay, but that's only in certain cases and biblically not. So biblically
you broke it and put it back together it would be טהור.
tahor. Yes.
So it has to be broken into pieces small enough so that
none of them can
contain—no, but it—but anyway we're not discussing that. There is discussion about,
about how much it has to be, to what degree it has
to be broken up. But, but it's not true that no piece
can be usable, yes.
Apologize for the elementary nature of this question. How if you sit
on a couch, yes, how do you make that טהור? tahor?
You dunk it in a מקוה. mikva. It might ruin the couch
in the process. Okay, so then don't make it טהור, tahor, live
with a טמא tamei couch.
That's how—so if someone sat on that couch
it's done until you bring it to—yeah. Yeah.
And how do you make that—what?
טמא tamei the wagon?
You get a big מקוה, mikva, you go into the ocean. I'm
serious, so then fine, so you leave it as טמא, tamei but
those are your options, right.
You're going to contaminate you right automatically as an אב, av, right?
So anyone sits on that couch forever? Right, yes. What if the
couch has
plastic
covers like our
grandparents?
Oh, so—well the plastic cover, that's a good example about the הלכות
halachos of a משכב, mishkav, because plastic isn't טמא, tamei but the
plastic cover wouldn't save the couch underneath because again that's the principle
of even if you're separated and you're not touching. So that would
be—that's an excellent example about טומאת מדרס, tumas midras, you know, going
not mattering if it's separated. Yes.
If I touch, but if I touch the outside of an earthenware
vessel, yes, it's not טמא. tamei? Right. So why would it be
a surprise it's going to have different
rules?
It does have different rules, but we have to prove that this
is one of the different rules that it cannot become a משכב.
mishkav. Okay. So that's the הלכה. halacha. By the way תוספות Tosafot
points out that it's not—it's a little imprecise when it says טהרה
במקוה tahara b'mikva because a זב zav actually has to go into
מים חיים, mayim chayim, live water, which means not collected rainwater but
it has to be like a natural well or a spring or
so on, a natural body of water. But anyway, but that we're
not focusing on. Even if it was something that, that you know
that you could bring to a מקוה, mikva, that would be enough.
But if something will remain טמא tamei? then it cannot become a
משכב. mishkav. Okay, so that's how we know to exclude pottery from
the principle of מדרס. midras. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא, D'bei Rabbi Yishmael
tana, the house of Rabbi Yishmael we taught, כמשכב נדתה יהיה לה,
k'mishkav nidatah yihyeh lah, the other example there are three people that
Like the משכב mishkav of a נדה niddah it
shall be for her, referring to, I believe, the פסוק pasuk is
by a זבה. zavah. Okay, but again, מקיש משכבה לה משכב נדתה,
matkish mishkava lah mishkav niddatah, the משכב mishkav of her נדה, niddah,
so therefore it connects the משכב mishkav to her. יהיה לה, yihye
lah, shall be for her. So מה היא אית לה טהרה במקוה,
mah hi it lah tahara b'mikvah, the same way she can go
to a מקוה, mikvah, אף משכבה נמי אית לה טהרה במקוה, af
mishkava nami it lah tahara b'mikvah, her משכב mishkav would only be
something that could be taken to a מקוה. mikvah. So you can't
have a משכב mishkav out of חרס, cheres, which cannot go to
a
מקוה. mikvah. לאפוקי כלי חרס דלית ליה טהרה במקוה, l'apukei kli cheres
d'leite tahara b'mikvah, this would exclude כלי חרס kli cheres that it
cannot be purified in a מקוה. mikvah. Okay, so that's how we
know to exclude pottery. We happened to mention that in passing by
discussing this
ספינת חרס sefinat cheres and כלי חרס klei cheres and so on.
So now we have clarified why חרס cheres cannot become טומאת מדרס.
tumat midras. Now מתיב רבי אילא. mativ Rabi Ila. רבי אילא Rabi
Ila asks on this idea that the only things that can become
מדרס midras are things that can be taken into a מקוה. mikvah.
מפץ דמת מנאיין. mapatz d'met minayin. So this is a focus of
this of what we're about to quote, of this ברייתא braita is
to make a different point. We're going to though learn something out
from the assumptions of this ברייתא. braita. But the focus is, how
do you know that a mat can become טומאת מת? tumat met?
A mat is, let's say you have a mat made out of
wood or made out of reeds or hemp or whatever, you've got
your mat. So that is what? That is a wood vessel. Okay,
it's עץ. etz. Although a question of if let's say hemp or
reeds are exactly wood, we'll discuss that but let's not worry about
that right now. A wood vessel can only become טמא tamei? if
it has a בית קיבול, beit kibbul, right? If it has a
receptacle, which doesn't mean flat. I mean flat effectively it is true,
like a table here is a great receptacle because it's flat, right?
But a receptacle actually means like a curved receptacle
so that something stays in it, can't like roll off of it.
So anyway, so a normal mat is not considered to have a
בית קיבול. beit kibbul. If it doesn't have a בית קיבול, beit
kibbul, then you would say it can't be טמא מת. tamei met.
But there's one area and this is what I alluded to before,
that some of the normal rules don't apply. And that's the area
of מדרס. midras. מדרס midras on the one hand we just learned
that some things will never be מדרס midras like pottery vessels, but
on the other hand, מדרס midras the primary focus is does it
function as a seat? And we don't go by the normal questions
about if it's wood it has to have a בית קיבול, beit
kibbul, etc. So therefore, if you have a mat, it will and
then it will become טמא מדרס tamei midras because it's made as
a seat, it functions as a seat, we don't ask these other
questions.
Well, yes, but let's pretend like they say of a bath mat.
Yes, actually, yes, something that's also made for standing on it would
be included, that is true. So that is the idea of מדרס.
midras. מדרס midras does not and that's why I said before also,
these ideas can it be carried empty or full? Those are not
so relevant by מדרס. midras. By מדרס midras the basic question is,
can it function as a seat, as something that you put your
weight on, you rest on, you stand on and so on? So
a mat can be a מדרס. midras. Now what we want to
know is, if this mat which can be a מדרס, midras, can
it also become טומאת מת? tumat met? Can it get in as
it were through the back door? You try to come in through
the front door, you want to become טמא מת, tamei met, as
if you wanted to. טמא מת tamei met is טמא tamei through
touching a dead body. Okay, so that's coming in through the front
door of normal טומאות. tumot. We ask you a question. What's the
question is? As wood, do you have a בית קיבול? beit kibbul?
The answer is no, so we turn you away at the front
door, right? So this is my little personification. But if you say,
ah, but you got into the מדרס midras because you're a mat,
you can be used by a זב. zav. So you're in the
זב zav category of מדרס. midras. Once you're in that category you
get in the back door, you could also become טמא טומאת מת.
tamei tumat met. Once you're a type of a vessel that could
be a מדרס, midras, that's made as a seat and could be
a מדרס midras for a זב, zav, then you're so weighty as
it were that you even are able to become טומאת מת tumat
met even though you don't satisfy the normal criteria. And that is
the point of this ברייתא. braita. How do you know that this
thing, that this mat could become טמא טומאת מת tamei tumat met
of a dead body even though it doesn't have a receptacle? ודין
הוא, v'din hu, it makes sense to say so. מה פחים קטנים
שטהורים בזב טמאים במת. mah pachim ktanim shet'horim b'zav t'meiyim b'met. So
this is like יעקב אבינו Yaakov Avinu went back for the פחים
קטנים. pachim ktanim. So anyway, so this is a famous example where
פחים קטנים pachim ktanim are used in a halachic context. So what's
the story about little vessels? That they are טהור בזב tahor b'zav
and they're טמא tamei with a for in a case of a
dead body. What does that mean? You have a little pottery vessel
that imagine like those little perfume bottles. You ever go like to
the Metropolitan Museum and you see those tiny little perfume bottles? You
know what I'm talking about? So let's say you had one thing
that was really small like that, or a really small hole that
is made out of pottery. Now, how could that thing become טמא?
tamei Well, how do normally do you get pottery טמא? tamei. You
touch the inside. Okay, how do you get anything inside that? I
mean you could sort of get a liquid inside, but if you're
a זב, zav, how would you make it טמא? tamei. You can't
get even your smallest finger inside. So תוספות Tosafot ask that. We'll
get to that in a minute. So רש"י Rashi says maybe you'll
say you could get your hair inside, right? Because hair if a
זב zav touches something even with his hair. We'll get the spit,
we'll get the spit. Let's first talk about his body. Oh you
said and let's first talk about his body. Okay, so a זב,
zav, right, even if he touches something with the hair on his
body, it's like he touched it. רש"י Rashi says so yes, you
could get hair inside, but that doesn't like you touched it. You
have to be able to actually touch it yourself. Something that you
could never touch, like this, because you could never get any of
your skin inside, your finger inside, would not be able to be
טמא tamei. even if you got your hair inside. And רש"י Rashi
says wait, but I got another idea says רש"י. Rashi. Remember yesterday
we learned about היסט? hesset? If you move something, you make it
טמא tamei, even if you don't touch it. And that applies even
to a כלי חרס. kli cheres. Even though a כלי חרס kli
cheres you have to touch on the inside, but if you move
it, since you've effectively moved the inside as well, it's like you
touched the inside. So what about why can't you move this vessel?
So רש"י Rashi says again, no, היסט hesset only makes something טמא
tamei. because it's as if you touched it. So again, this type
of a thing, which you cannot touch on the inside, even though
you could touch with your hair, even though you could move, all
of those other things are because they're like you touched it, and
if you're not able to touch it, it does not become טמא.
tamei Now תוספות Tosafos asks the question that David and Michael asked:
well, you could spit inside, and the spit of a זב zav
is טמא. tamei תוספות Tosafos doesn't have an answer, but presumably the
point is fine, but that's טומאה tumah from the spit of a
זב, zav, at least טומאה tumah directly from the זב, zav, that's
a separate אב הטומאה, av hatumah, that's not the זב zav is
making it טמא. tamei, His spit, which is itself an אב הטומאה
av hatumah makes it טמא, tamei. but the זב zav himself cannot
make these vessels טמא. tamei. So you have these little pottery vessels
that a זב zav cannot touch on the inside, that they cannot
become טמא tamei through the זב. zav. But they can become טמא
tamei by a dead body. How? Because if they're in the under
the same roof of a dead body, right, the dead body doesn't
have to get its finger inside of this, under the same roof,
it's like the air gets in there and makes it טמא, tamei
so that can be טמא. tamei So the basic point of these
פכים קטנים pachim ktanim are just to prove that you can have
certain things that are טהור tahor by a זב zav and still
by a מת, meis, by a dead body, it's they're able to
become טמא. tamei So you have a case where things are more
susceptible, at least in this case, to the טומאה tumah of a
dead body than the טומאה tumah of a זב. zav. That's these
little vessels. So these are טהורים בזב וטמאים במת. tehorim bezav utmei
bemeis. So מפץ, mapatz, a mat שטמא בזב, shetamei bezav, that's טמא
tamei,
by a זב zav because it's a mat, it's מדרס, midras, so
אינו דין שיהא טמא במת? eino din sheyehei tamei bemeis? How much
more so should it become טמא tamei. with a dead body? Okay,
so that's the basic point. And by the way, this is the
הלכה. halacha The הלכה is is that things that are able to
become a טומאת מדרס tumat midras are also able to become טמא
מת tamei meis because of this little קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So
you don't need, even if you don't satisfy like I said, you
can't get in the front door, you're not a wood vessel with
a receptacle, because you're still a מדרס, midras, you're made for reclining
or sitting, and therefore could become טמא tamei? for a זב, zav,
you're also able to become טמא tamei. with other טומאות tumas as
well. That's all very interesting, very important and then terms of the
you know, sort of this backdoor idea. But what's but our focus
is not on that whole argument. Our focus is on the implicit
point, which is that a mat can become a מדרס. midras. Now
why can a mat become a מדרס? midras? A mat doesn't have
טהרה במקוה. tahara bemikvah. So it says ואמאי, ve'amai, why can a
mat be מדרס? midras? הא לית ליה טהרה במקוה. Ha leis lei
tahara bemikvah. It doesn't have טהרה tahara in a מקוה. mikvah. Why
does a mat not have טהרה במקוה? tahara bemikvah? So רש"י Rashi
says, again, this is quite ironic, רש"י Rashi says well, it's a
wood vessel without a receptacle. So the Torah only spoke about wood
vessels with receptacles being טמא tamei and putting them in the מקוה.
mikvah. It never spoke about wood vessels without receptacles. So since right,
a wood vessel without a בית קיבול beit kibul is never discussed
in the Torah. So the same way it's not discussed for becoming
טמא, tamei. it's not discussed for becoming טהור. tahor. So therefore, you
can't
take it in the
מקוה. mikvah. תוספות Tosafos just disagrees with it. He says no, no,
no. He brings other גמרות Gemaras and said wood vessels even without
a בית קיבול beit kibul they can be taken into the מקוה
mikvah if they get טמא. tamei, How do they get טמא? tamei
Like this case, so used for a מדרס. midras. He says no,
we're talking specifically about like a hemp mat. A hemp mat is
actually not a wood vessel. A hemp is different than wood and
actually he says biblically it would be if it touched other things
totally טהור, tahor, even if it had a receptacle. It's not a
normal type of a material that is normally able to become טמא.
tamei? And that way it's sort of like the flip side of
חרס. cheres. חרס cheres becomes טמא tamei. without ever being able to
become טהור. tahor. Other types of materials, I don't know imagine you
made it out of plastic, right? So other types of materials they
can't become they don't have טהרה במקוה tahara bemikvah because the Torah
never because they were not materials that ever become טמא. tamei So
of course they don't have טהרה במקוה. tahara bemikvah. So but the
גמרא is saying is ah, so here from the other side of
the coin, why should this mat out of out of hemp be
able to be a מדרס midras if מקוה mikvah is irrelevant to
it? Now מקוה mikvah is irrelevant for a different purpose, right, because
it sort of never becomes טמא, tamei. but again the point is
but if you're going to make it טמא tamei as a מדרס,
midras, then your... You're stuck because the תורה never allows for a
מקוה Mikveh to make it טהור. tahor. Okay so that's our question.
So the upshot is we said pottery cannot be a מדרס Midras
because it will be stuck, it won't be able to be טהור
tahor in a מקוה. Mikveh. So it says how about this mat?
This mat also will be stuck. For whatever reason it doesn't have
a receptacle, it's made out of a different material, but whatever reason
is the תורה never explicitly said, or the תורה never said you
could make this טהור tahor in a מקוה. Mikveh. So how could
this become a מדרס? Midras? How could this get a permanent טומאה
tumah if it cannot, you know, if how can it be a
מדרס? Midras? So we're saying...
So you're taking the opposite side, that if something we know can't
become טהור tahor that means it certainly can't become טמא?
tamei No, no, no, we're just... forget it, we're not discussing the
טמא. tamei. We just want to work on the assumption of this
ברייתא Braita that a mat, a flat mat, maybe not even made
out of wood, can be a מדרס. Midras. Why is that if
you could never take it to a מקוה? Mikveh? And you said
you have to be able to be able to take it to
a מקוה. Mikveh. So let's say, ואמאי, Ve'amai, why could this mat
become a מדרס? Midras? והא לית ליה טהרה במקוה, Ve'ha leit lei
tahara be'mikveh, you'll never be able to take it to a מקוה
Mikveh and make it טהור. tahor. אמר ליה רבי חנינא, Amar lei
Rabbi Chanina, it's different. שאני התם דאיכא במיניה. Shani hatam de'ika be'minei.
That's different because at least things in the same general category can
be taken to a מקוה. Mikveh. What does that mean? Other wood
vessels, if it has... vessels with receptacles, although תוספות Tosafot says even
if this is hemp and it's not wood, but it's still in
the broad category of wood because, you know, it's still things that
grow from the ground and so on. But hemp clothing? What? Hemp
clothing? I don't know, maybe. Fine. Okay, let's... please, we're not talking
about that.
Okay, so a receptacle big enough to hold a pomegranate and a
person could sleep on it.
We're not talking about the pomegranate stuff anymore.
No, but we said בית קיבול... beit kibbul...
yes, but that's the whole point, a mat doesn't need a receptacle.
A mat is מדרס Midras without a receptacle because it's made for
sleeping or sitting or reclining.
So it has to be able to hold...
it's flat. No, that was my point, that the normal... that's why
I said it couldn't go in the front door, the normal criteria
is not satisfied. It does not have a receptacle. But because it's
made for מדרס, Midras, for sitting or lying or standing, it's able
to become טמא tamei as a מדרס. Midras. The טומאה tumah of
מדרס Midras of seats does not have those other criteria.
So when you say receptacle, I don't know why I can't understand
this, receptacle doesn't mean a hole?
It does, actually. It does. But that's not a criteria for מדרס.
Midras. That's not a criteria for seats.
Something that's flat has to...
except for מדרס. Midras. For מדרס, Midras, this category, that... that does
not need those criteria. That's what I'm saying, the normal... otherwise it
does, right. Okay, so anyway, so the answer is, look, it's different
than pottery. Pottery never makes it into a מקוה. Mikveh. This mat,
which is again, is flat, doesn't need a בית קיבול beit kibbul
because it's a מדרס, Midras, it's used as a... it's used as
a mat, it's used as something for sitting or standing or whatever,
this mat can become a מדרס. Midras. Why? Because although a non-receptacle
wood object might not have טהרה tahara in a מקוה, Mikveh, or
certainly if it's not out of wood, it's out of hemp, but
it's not... this material is still in the category of things that
are taken to a מקוה. Mikveh. If it's made with a receptacle,
it would be able to have a מקוה. Mikveh. Or, if תוספות
Tosafot says even if hemp doesn't, but wood does, that's roughly in
the same category. So it's not as categorically excluded, and therefore it
can become a מדרס. Midras. That's the answer. It's very different than
pottery. So the גמרא says... so Michael doesn't like it, so you
know what, he... whoever... who was the one who made this point?
Rabbi
Ila. So that's what רבי חנינא said back to רבי אילא. Rabbi
Ila. So רבי אילא Rabbi Ila said back to him... אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so רבי אילא Rabbi Ila said back to him, רחמנא
ליצלן מהאי דעתא. Rachmana litzlan me'hai da'ata. God should save us from
such an opinion. Okay? Where did that come from? Anyway, but he
basically said what a crazy סברא sevara that is! If the thing
can't become טהור, tahor, it can't become טהור. tahor. Who cares if
well, it's in the general category of things that could have a
מקוה. Mikveh. This thing can't be טהור, tahor, it shouldn't be able
to be a מדרס. Midras. And so he said back to him,
אדרבה, Adaraba, the opposite, רחמנא ליצלן מדעתא דידך. Rachmana litzlan mi'da'ata didach.
God should save us from your opinion. So there's a similar exchange
in בבא קמא Bava Kamma and כתובות, Ketubot, you see in the
side, and I didn't check, but from what I remember, I think
it's the same אמוראי, Amora'ei, that they're the ones that went back
and forth, you know, with that line. Anyway, okay, וטעמא מאי? Ve'ta'ama
mai? So look, so justify it though. What is the reason that
being in the category is enough even if it can't actually be
taken to the מקוה? Mikveh? So תרי קראי כתיבי. Trei krai ktivi.
There are two פסוקים. pesukim. כתיב איש אשר יגע במשכבו. Ktiv ish
asher yigah be'mishkavo.
Somebody touches the משכב mishkav of the זב. zav. And whenever משכבו,
mishkavo, we know that it has to be like him, it has
to be able to be taken to a מקוה. Mikveh. וכתיב וכתיב
וכל המשכב אשר ישכב עליו הזב יטמא. Ve'kh'tiv ve'khol ha'mishkav asher yishkav
alav ha'zav yitma. Any
משכב mishkav that he sits on, without connecting it to him, doesn't
call it his משכב, mishkav, יטמא. yitma. So what is it? Does
it have to be like him or not like him? הכיצד? Ha'keitzad?
How do you reconcile this? So יש במינו אע"פ דלית ליה טהרה
במקוה. Yesh be'mino af al pi de'leit lei tahara be'mikveh. If, if
it's
in
the category, although it
doesn't
have טהרה tahara in a מקוה, Mikveh, in... even though then even
though of things like this can be taken to the מקוה, mikveh,
then it could be a משכב mishkav even though it itself cannot
be taken to the מקוה. mikveh. So like this hemp mat. So
as long as it's in the category of things, that's enough for
becoming טמא. tamei. אין במינו, ein bemino,
but when it's not even in the category like pottery, that's when
we say משכבו לו. mishkavo lo. Then it then it has to
be like him, it has to be able to be taken to
the מקוה. mikveh. So basically it says we've got two competing פסוקים,
pesukim, one פסוק pasuk that says like him and the other says
not like him. The way we reconcile it is its things that
at least are of the types of things that you would take
to the מקוה. mikveh. So pottery is never of that so you
can't have a pottery a pottery thing that's a משכב mishkav that's
מדרס, midras, but things that are of wood and hemp even if
in this circumstance not they're in the category of things that are
yes and therefore they can be a משכב. mishkav. And again you
could be a משכב mishkav of a זב zav without having a
בית קיבול beis kibul that goes a different way. And then once
you're in the זב zav category you through the back door get
into the מת meis category as well. Okay so that's that's one
explanation of why of why pottery cannot be a משכב mishkav because
it is not something that is brought to the מקוה, mikveh, nothing
pottery is never nothing in that category ever goes into the מקוה.
mikveh. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, מדרס כלי חרס טהור
מהכא, midras kli cheres tahor mei-hacha,
I'll give you a different reason why pottery vessels cannot be a
מדרס. midras. וכל כלי פתוח אשר אין צמיד פתיל עליו. vechol kli
patuach asher ein tzamid patil alav.
It says by a by pottery in a in a room in
which there's a dead body, any open vessel that does not have
a sealed cover over it will become טמא tamei because then it's
like the טומאה tumah goes through the air space and goes into
the air of the pottery vessel and pottery becomes טמא tamei through
something on the inside. But if it's covered with a sealed cover
then it remains טהור tahor because it's like the טומאה tumah doesn't
get in. So he says הא יש צמיד פתיל עליו ha yesh
tzamid patil alav then טהור הוא. tahor hu. So okay so big
deal, so he says one minute, מאי לאו עסקינן דיחדינהו לישיבת נדה?
mai lav askinan de-yachdinahu l'yeshivat niddah?
Why should the תורה assume that all pottery vessels with seals are
טהור? tahor? I'll give you a scenario of a pottery vessel with
a seal in the in the room of a dead body that
should be טמא. tamei. What is it? Is that it's a pottery
vessel used for sitting, used for משכב mishkav and maybe you know
it's even set aside like we were discussing the other day about
what did people you know how did they handle it if something
anything a woman sat on or touched when she was a נדה
niddah remains טמא tamei until you brought it to the מקוה, mikveh,
right? So how does that you know affect the house of a
כהן? kohen? So maybe there were designated seats which is getting to
this whole question of how much did they have you know a
sort of shared space or how much was isolated at least for
כהנים kohanim during that period.
So let's say you had a designated seat this is the נדה
niddah seat, so it's designated for for מדרס midras for sitting, it's
designated for you know for a woman who's a נדה niddah to
sit on it. So it should be if if there's a concept
of משכב mishkav it should be able to become טמא. tamei Something
that's able to become טמא tamei cannot serve as a חציצה chatzitzah
a block from טומאה getting in. So why does this pottery vessel
with the seal why does it remain טהור tahor if it's something
that could be a משכב mishkav it should also be able to
become טמא in this scenario. And since the תורה says that this
is always טהור tahor when it has a seal on it you
see that there's no other way of it becoming טמא. Another way
of saying this is is that it can only become טמא through
the inside and therefore if it's got a seal it remains טהור.
tahor. A משכב mishkav is something that becomes טמא from the outside
because of the way it's used on the outside of it. So
since the תורה says once you've sealed the opening you're safe that
shows that it cannot be a משכב mishkav and that's how you
know pottery vessels cannot be a משכב. mishkav.
That's a much simpler explanation.
You think so? All right I don't know because there's a whole
תוספות Tosafot explaining some of the details which I didn't go into.
Oh okay.
Let's explain it very simply.
All right let's start we have a few minutes with the next
משנה. Now we move from טהרות taharos to זרעים. zeraim. This is
a little this is a little like you know
birds-eye view of a lot of different areas of
ש"ס. shas. So we did טהרות taharos now we're moving on to
זרעים. zeraim.
Is this circular about the משכב mishkav and the pottery vessel because
you're saying a pottery vessel could not receive משכב? mishkav?
Right but the proof is that were it able to receive משכב
mishkav then it would become טמא even in the even in the
house of a dead body. Right okay. So now we look at
here's another one. מניין לערוגה שהיא ששה על ששה טפחים? minayin le-arugah
she-hi sheishah al sheishah tefachim? How do you know about a like
a
what do you call it a garden not a garden what's the
word anyway a bed a flower bed or a vegetable garden you
know that is six by six טפחים? tefachim? A טפח tefach is
about three three inches I'd say foot and a half by foot
and a half three and a half inches or so. וזורע בתוכה
חמשה זרעונין v'zorea betochah chamesh zerounin that you can have five different
seeds types of plant. ארבע בארבע רוחות הערוגה ואחת באמצע. arba be-arba
ruchot ha-arugah v'achat be-emtza. Four on the four sides and one in
the middle. So if you look at the picture in רש"י Rashi
okay there's six by six each little box is a טפח tefach
by a טפח. tefach. The the shaded area are rows of different
types so let's say you have one row of carrots one of
celery one of I don't know potatoes one of cabbage... Okay, and
the little corners are left unplanted and you have one plant of
some fifth type of thing in the middle. How do you know
you can do that and that's not a כלאים Kilayim problem? שנאמר
because the פסוק says, כי כארץ תוציא צמחה, Ki ka'aretz totzi tzimchah,
because like the land will it sprout come forth, וכגנה uk'ginah and
like a and like a flower bed or whatever, like a garden
זרועיה zeirueha its seeds תצמיח tatzmiach will sprout. זרעה Zar'ah it says
its seed singular, it doesn't say אלא זרועיה ela zeirueha its seeds.
So still, how do you get five? So let's read the first
line of the גמרא. מאי משמע? Mai mashma? How do you get
five out of that? אמר רב יהודה, כי כארץ תוציא צמחה, Ki
ka'aretz totzi tzimchah, תוציא totzi חד, chad, take out is one, צמחה
tzimchah its sprout is חד chad is another one, that's two. הרי
תרי, Harei trei, that gets you two. זרועיה, Zeirueha, its seeds plural,
תרי, trei, הרי ארבע, harei arba, that's four. תצמיח Tatzmiach חד, chad,
and then the other תצמיח tatzmiach החמשה, ha-chamesha, that's five. Now what
are the points going on here? So very important, let's understand the
principle. כלאים, Kilayim,
where the issue is כלאים, Kilayim, right, mixing seeds. רש"י Rashi makes
the very critical point that and we'll see this is debated, רש"י
Rashi תוספות Tosafot parameters, but I'm going to start today by telling
you רש"י. Rashi. That by כלאים Kilayim it doesn't really matter if
the if they are the different plants are drawing nutrients from one
another. The definition of כלאים Kilayim is requires that they be visibly
separate. Okay, רש"י's Rashi's proof is if we have a budding yard,
I can plant, you know, my you know your you know your
seeds right up to the fence, I can plant them right up
to the fence, they're an inch apart, but it's not כלאים Kilayim
because they're separated by a fence. Okay, so therefore in this case
where you've got you know four rows like this, because this row
is in different direction than the rows near it, it's not like
you did this and then you made a little gap and you
continued doing this in a different type, then it looks all together.
But this doesn't look together, right? This is in this direction, this
is in this direction. So as long as there's even the tiniest
gap here, you're okay. This is not כלאים Kilayim with this, the
fact that they're going in different directions visually makes them different. The
one in the middle, because it's not going in a different direction,
is most likely to become כלאים Kilayim even though it's furthest away,
but there's no different direction. It's the different direction that saves the
ones on the edges. So there when there is nothing like a
different direction, what you need to define them as separate is they
have to be separated by three טפח. tefach. So therefore since it's
six by six, you've got the one in the middle, that's got
three טפח tefach in each direction. Now if you think about it
not really, because because there's the thickness of what's here and there's
the thickness of this row. Okay, so we can talk about that,
but the basic point is these are not כלאים Kilayim because they're
different direction and there's a little gap and that's visual, this is
not כלאים Kilayim because it's just separated by three in all sides.
תוספות Tosafot will describe it differently, but that's how רש"י Rashi describes
it. One last point and we'll mention this again tomorrow, is that
רש"י Rashi says all of this is rabbinic because רש"י Rashi says
the only biblical כלאים Kilayim is when it involves the vine, כלאי
הכרם. kilay ha-kerem. When it involves things other than the vine, it's
all rabbinic. תוספות Tosafot disagree, תוספות Tosafot says no, it's very clear
that there's כלאי זרעים kilay zra'im of seeds and plants or whatever
that is not about the vine, that is also biblical. It is
true that the גמרא's give greater weight to the כלאי הכרם kilay
ha-kerem when it involves the vine, but that's regarding the point that
if you plant כלאים, Kilayim, what grows is forbidden, and that idea
that the produce of כלאים Kilayim is forbidden, that could be limited
to כלאי הכרם, kilay ha-kerem, but the prohibition of planting כלאים Kilayim
applies by other seeds as well. But רש"י Rashi very interestingly says
no, he says the only biblical prohibition of planting כלאים Kilayim is
with the vine, when it doesn't involve the vine it's all rabbinic.
So we will pick up with this whole discussion tomorrow as we
move from פאה Peah to זרעים. Zra'im.
Wait, what does רמב"ם Rambam say about that?
About the כלאי הכרם kilay ha-kerem versus כלאי זרעים? kilay zra'im? I'd
have to check, I don't
remember.